<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bioloogy on David&#39;s musings and ramblings.</title>
    <link>https://musings.dcaro.es/tags/bioloogy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Bioloogy on David&#39;s musings and ramblings.</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>© David Caro 2024</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2024 20:59:24 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://musings.dcaro.es/tags/bioloogy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Book: What Is Life? ★★★☆☆</title>
      <link>https://musings.dcaro.es/posts/2024-03-15-book---what-is-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2024 20:59:24 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://musings.dcaro.es/posts/2024-03-15-book---what-is-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For my birthday I got a bunch of books from the&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://global.oup.com/academic/content/series/o/oxford-landmark-science-ols/&#34;&gt;oxford landmark science&lt;/a&gt;,&#xA;and this is the second one that I&amp;rsquo;ve read so far.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the book, the author introduces several of the main properties of life as we&#xA;know it:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Complex: alive entities are really complex&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Purposeful: living things seem to follow a goal, birds build nests, parents&#xA;care for their offspring, etc.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Dynamic: life is always moving, old cells are dying and new ones get created&#xA;all the time, it&amp;rsquo;s a bubbling non-stop.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Diverse: life adapts, changes, and continues adapting. Change seems to be&#xA;inherent to all this process.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Out of equilibrium: it seems that life, with all the dynamism and change,&#xA;creates systems that are quite far from energetic equilibrium as we understand&#xA;it, seemingly breaking the second law of thermodynamics.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Chiral: there&amp;rsquo;s many molecules involved in life as we know it, that have a&#xA;&amp;ldquo;handedness&amp;rdquo; to them, like DNA, and for some reason, the vast majority of them&#xA;are only find with the same handedness in living beings, like amino-acids are&#xA;left handed, while sugars are right handed. But the question is, given that&#xA;the inorganic world is a mixture of both, why does the biological world become&#xA;homochiral?&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The author then elucidates that in order to know what is life, we have to&#xA;understand it, understand how it happened. Now, &amp;ldquo;how it happened&amp;rdquo; gets divided&#xA;in two questions, one historical, and one a-historical:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
